Abraham: In a time where almost half
of UK residents have purchased at
least one smart device since the start
of the covid19 pandemic, the threat
to users and their networks from
cyber attacks has never been greater.
Everyday products such as smart
watches, TV's cameras and other
smart appliances offer huge benefits
but are vulnerable to cyber attack.
To counter this threat the Government
is planning a new law to make sure
that virtually all smart devices
meet new security requirements.
Some of the main points
of the law will include.
• “Customers must be informed at
the point of sale the duration of
time for which a smart device will
receive security software updates”
• A ban on manufacturers using
universal default passwords, such
as ‘password’ or ‘admin’, that are
often pre-set in a device’s factory
settings and are easily guessable
• Manufacturers will be required
to provide a public point of
contact to make it simpler for
anyone to report a vulnerability.”
Smartphones are also to be covered by the
planned 'Secure by Design' legislation.
Many people keep their phones for
more than four years whilst some
companies only offer security
updates for just over 2 years.
Security updates are important
in protecting users against cyber
criminals and tech firms need to be
more up front about how long they
support the security of devices.
Tech associations including the Internet
of Secure Things [IoXT] which includes
large companies like Google, Amazon and
Facebook support this new legislation
to boost the security of smart devices.
The government is also looking at research
reports providing further evidence:
Development for this legislation
has been by the Department for
Digital, Culture, Media and Sport
[DCMS], in conjunction with the
National Cyber Security Centre [NCSC]
“The aim of this Code of Practice is
to support all parties involved in the
development, manufacturing and retail
of consumer IoT with a set of guidelines
to ensure that products are secure by
design and to make it easier for people
to stay secure in a digital world.”